<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pater noster spoken of ye sinner God answerynge him at euery peticyon.</title>
            <title>Lord's prayer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103233</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 715:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pater noster spoken of ye sinner God answerynge him at euery peticyon.</title>
                  <title>Lord's prayer.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Godfray,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1535]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title within decorative panels.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3383:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter ſpoken of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sinner: God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerynge
him at euery pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticyon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3383:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3383:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The pr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpoken of the ſinner.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Oure father whiche arte in heuen / what a great ſpace is
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the and vs? Howe therfore ſhall we thy chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren here on erthe / 
banyſſhed and exiled from the in this vale of myſery and
wretchedneſſe / come home to the into our natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall countrey?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God.</speaker>
               <p>☞ The chylde honoureth his father / &amp; the ſeruaunt
his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. If I be your father / wher is myne honour? If I be your lorde / 
where is my feare? Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lachias .i. For my name tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe you and by your meanes
is blaſpemed / rayled vpon / and euyll ſpoken of. Eſaias .lii.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:3383:3"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ Helas o father that is truth / we knowlege our ſynne
and tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpace / neuertheleſſe / yet be thou a mercyfull father / and dele
nat with vs accordige to our deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges / neither iuge vs by the
rygorouſneſſe of thy lawe / but gyue vs grace that we maye ſo lyue / 
that thy holy name maye be halowed &amp; ſancttfyed in vs.</p>
               <p>And kepe oure hertes that we neither do nor ſpeake / no / 
that we nat ones thinke our purpoſe any thynge / but that whiche is to thine
honour and praiſe / and aboue al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges make thy name and honour to be
ſought of vs / and nat our own name &amp; vaine glorie. and of thy myghty
po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer brynge to paſſe in vs / that <pb facs="tcp:3383:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>we
maye loue and feare the / as a ſonne his father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God.</speaker>
               <p>☞ How can myne honour and name be halowed amonge you / 
whan your hertes and though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are alwayes enclyned to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll / and ye in
bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuyte vnder ſynne: moreouer ſeynge that no man can ſynge
my laude and prayſe in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge countrey. Pſal. cxxxvi.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ O father that is truthe / we fele our membres / ye / 
and alſo the very hertes of vs prone and redy to ſynne / and that the
worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / the fleſſhe / and the deuyll / rule in vs / and expell the dewe
honoure of thyne holye name. Wherfore we beſeche the moſte
<pb facs="tcp:3383:4"/>mercifull father / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue that
thou haſt vnto thy ſonne Chriſt helpe vs out of this myſerable bondage
/ and let thy kyngdom come to dryue out the ſynne / to loſe the bondes of
Sathan / to tame the fleſſh / to make vs righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſe and parfeyte / and
to cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vnto the / that thou only mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte raygne in vs / and that we maye
be thy kyngdome and poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſyon / and the obey with all our power and
ſtrength / bothe within and without.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God.</speaker>
               <p>☞ Whom I helpe / them I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye. And whom I make
ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge / ſafe / riche / and good / them I kyll / condempne / and caſt
them awaye / make theym beggers / and brynge them to
<pb facs="tcp:3383:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>nought. But ſo to be cured
of me ye wyll nat ſuffre. Pſalmo. lxxvii. Howe than ſhall I hele you / ye
/ and what can I do mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re? Eſaias .v.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ That is to vs great ſorowe and grefe / that we can
neither vnderſtande nor ſuffre thy hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom hande / wherfore helpe dere
father / open our eyes / and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke pacience in vs / that we may vnderſtande
thi holeſom hande and alſo pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſuffre thy god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly wyll to be
fulfylled in vs.</p>
               <p>Furthermore / though thy moſt holeſome cure be neuer ſo
payn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full vnto vs / yet go forwarde therwith / puniſſhe / bete / cutte / 
burne / diſtroy / bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to nought dampne / caſt downe vnto hell / 
<pb facs="tcp:3383:5"/>and do what ſo euer thou wilte that
thy wyll onely may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled and nat ours. Forbydde dere father / and in no
wyſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs to folow our owne good thoughtes and imagynations / neyther
to proſecute our owne wyll / meanynge / and purpoſe. For thy wyll and ours
ar clene contrary one to the other / thyne onely good / though it otherwy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
appere vnto our blynde reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and our euyll / though our blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneſſe
ſe it nat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God.</speaker>
               <p>☞ I am well ſerued and delte with all / that men loue
me with their lyppes / and theyr hertes are farre fro me / and whan I take them
in hande to make them better and to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de them / <pb facs="tcp:3383:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>than
ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne they backwarde / and in the middes of their cure / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le their helth is
a workyng / thei withdrawe them ſelues fro me: as thou redeſt. Pſal.
lxxvii.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conuerſi ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in die belli.</hi> They ar tourned backe
in the daye of battayle. That is to ſaye / they which began well / and
commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them ſelues vnto me / that I ſhulde take them in hande / and
cure them / are gone backe fro me in tyme of temptation / and kyllynge of the
fleſſhe / and are retourned to ſinne and vnto diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>honourynge of me
agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ O father it is true / no man can be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in his
owne ſtren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gth / in the ſeconde chapyter of the firſt of the Kynges. ye / 
and <pb facs="tcp:3383:6"/>who is able to ſuffre and a
byde before thyne hande / if thou thy ſelfe ſtrength &amp; conforte vs nat:
wherfore moſt mercyfull father take vs vnto thy cure / fulfyll thy wyll in vs
/ that we may be thy kingdome and inherytau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto thy laude and prayſynge.
Alſo dere father / ſtrength and confort vs in ſuch buſines with thy
holy worde. Gyue vs oure dayly bred / graue &amp; prynte thy dere ſonne
Ieſus in our hertes / that we ſtrengthed thorow him maye cherefully and
gladly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer and endure the diſtroyenge and kyllynge of our wyll / and
the fulfyllynge of thy wyll / ye / and ſhede out thy grace vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all
chriſtente / and ſende lerned pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes and prechers to tech vs thy
<pb facs="tcp:3383:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſonne Ieſus purely / and
to fede vs with the worde of thy holy goſpell / and nat with the dreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and
chaffe of fables &amp; mens doctryne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God.</speaker>
               <p>☞ It is nat good to caſt perles before ſwyne / 
neyther to gyue holy thinges / and the childrens bred vnto the dogges and
hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. ye ſynne contynually with out ceaſſyng / and though I let my
worde be preached amonge you neuer ſo moch / yet ye folow nat neither obey / 
but diſpyſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ O father haue mercy on vs / and denye vs nat that
breed of loue / it greueth vs fore / euen at the very herte rotes of vs / that
we can nat ſatiſfye thy worde and folow it. we deſyre the ther
<pb facs="tcp:3383:7"/>to haue pacyence with vs thy poore
and wretched chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to forgyue vs our treſpace and gyle / and iuge vs
nat after thy lawe / for no man is rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe in thy preſence. Loke on thy
promyſes / we forgyue oure treſpacers / and that wyth all our hertes / and
vnto ſuche haſt thou promyſed forgyuenes / nat that we thorowe ſuch
forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ar worthy of thy forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / but that thou arte trewe
/ and of thi grace and mercy haſt promyſed forgyuenes vnto all them that
forgyue their neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours / in this thy promyſe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore is all our hope and
truſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God</speaker>
               <p>☞ I forgyue you ofte / &amp; looſe you ofte / &amp; ye
neuer abyde ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte <pb facs="tcp:3383:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>/
children of lytle fayth are ye / ye can nat watche and endu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re with me a lytle
whyle / but at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tones fall againe into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Mathe. in the .xxvi.
chapter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ Weake are we o father / and feble / and the temptacyon
great and manyfolde in the fleſſh and in the worlde. Kepe vs father with
thy mightye power / and let vs nat fall in to temptatyon and ſynne agayne:
but gyue vs grace that we maye abyde ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge / and fyght manfully vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the ende / for withoute thy grace we can do nothynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ God.</speaker>
               <p>☞ I am rightuous / and right is my iudgement / and
therfore ſynne may nat be vnpuniſſhed / <pb facs="tcp:3383:8"/>ye
/ and ye muſt ſuffre euyll and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and as touchyng that ye haue
te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptatyon therby / that is your ſynnes faute only / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che compelleth me
thervnto / to kyll it &amp; to heale you. For ſinne can with none other
medycyne be drawen out of you / but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe aduerſyte and ſuffrynge of
euyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ The ſynner.</speaker>
               <p>☞ For as moch than as aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte / trybulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
afflyction / and euyll / whiche fyghte agaynſte ſynne gyue vs temptacyon / 
de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuer vs out of theym / fyniſſhe thy cure / and make vs thorowe hole / 
that we loſed from ſynne and euyll / maye be vnto the a kyngdome / to laude
/ to prayſe / and to ſanctify the. Amen</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3383:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> And ſeynge thou haſt taught vs thus to
praye / and haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed alſo to here vs / we hope and are ſure that
thou wylt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſly and mercyfully grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vs our peticions for thi verites
ſake / and to the honourynge of thy trueth. Amen,</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fynally ſome man wyll ſaye happely:
what and if I can nat beleue that my prayer is herde. I anſwere. Than do as
the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the poſſeſſed dyd in the .ix. of Marke / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt
ſayd vnto him. Yf thou couldeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue / all thynges are poſſyble vnto
him that beleueth. The father anſwered: I beleue lorde helpe myne vnbelefe.
That is to ſaye: Hele myne vnbelefe / <pb facs="tcp:3383:9"/>and
gyue me perfyte belefe / and ſtrength the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my faith / &amp;
encreaſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed at London by Thomas Godfray.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regali.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
